testing audio test test test okay good evening everyone now calling to order
this work session of Lancaster City Council for November 6 2025 we'll begin with a roll call mr. Harris I'll give you the honors for that one it's gonna
be brief for the moment Thank You madam president mr. med mr. Roya mr. Cleese miss Craig yeah miss Diaz mr. Hirsch here I'm president Baker here I do
expect additional members will be along very shortly but we will get started as this is a work session we don't need to wait for quorum so this meeting and its
participants are being recorded this evening a few other reminders this is a work session of council to review the ethics Commission recommendations for the ethics code as required by the Home Rule Charter as with all work sessions we have had so far this is not legislative or deliberative city
solicitor Barry Hanberger will review the recommendations and this evening
after each section we'll pause for any council questions and then public comment public comment is limited to three minutes per speaker and please
begin with your name and block of residence for the meeting record if you wish to make comment as with all of these work sessions as well members of council may submit questions directly to mr. Hanberger after the meeting again this is not a deliberative session all right and with that we will dive right in welcome and thank you for being here thank you good evening I know that four
members of the Ethics Commission are in the public tonight they've done a lot of hard work to get us to where we are this evening to follow up on council
presidents notes the previous work sessions were scheduled as committee meetings and committees of the whole this is actually not scheduled as a committee meeting
it is a public workshop as required by the charter from a history perspective the charter requires the creation of an ethics commission the commission is to provide recommendations to council council is to adopt the code prior to adopting the code council is to hold a public workshop regarding the matters that might be in the code so I'm just going to caution you again to make sure that because we did not advertise this as a meeting that for Sunshine Act purposes questions are fine but what you don't want to do council
members is be commenting opinions as to what should or shouldn't be in that would be deemed a deliberation but you're certainly welcome to have questions make comments but again not not something that would turn into a
deliberations so that we don't put you in the position of being in a meeting that is not been advertised as a meeting. That being said, the ethics commission that you appointed along with the controller and
the mayor met multiple times to review and discuss what should or shouldn't be in the
ethics code based on their review of the Charter their review of the state ethics
code which governs some but not all officials in the city of Lancaster and
review of other ethics codes that have been adopted for example the cities of Easton in Pittsburgh and they came to unanimous determinations not just a consensus about a series of recommendations and I afforded all of
you a memo regarding those so you have that and since the since you already have that I'm not going to spend a ton of time going through them I'm going to summarize them quickly they asked for a preamble and I will note to you that the
remainder of the presentation tonight will include my first version of a draft of the code which does incorporate the recommendations of the ethics Commission It obviously goes beyond the recommendations into detail Clarification that the scope of this is for public officials and city employees of the city of Lancaster to make sure that we define Certain items
More importantly than definitions one of the things that was left open was how to stagger terms and get the Commission organized So the recommendation for the staggered terms of the seven member Commission is two members to serve one year terms two members to serve two-year terms and three members to serve three-year terms, and they've actually reached agreement on who would serve on each in a way that assures that there's not one of the appointing bodies that's sort of controlling things at the time of the initial terms expiring, and that when terms do expire thereafter, it's a mix. The recommendations include sort of the scope of code violations to include conflicts of
interest excessive gifts or improper gratuities misuse of confidential
information use of your office improperly for either advocacy or influence improper use of city resources and property a post employment restriction on appearing before boards and commissions dealing with what we call two minutes or nominal value and setting that their recommendation is at We'll talk about that a little bit more this evening. And then penalties for violation of the act.
With respect to most of you are aware you have to file statements of financial disclosure as elected officials. The Ethics Commission's recommendation is to keep the current state act as to who is required to file those the same. But the Ethics Commission should have the right to review those if an issue regarding
ethics code comes up those disclosures under the state act include obviously your sources of income gifts given debts of certain value and more
the commission is recommending that complaints be investigated by independent professionals in other words an investigator hired by the commission that the commission would be the entity to supervise the investigators so as to assure both privacy and independence flexibility in the investigation reviewing and resolution process to make sure that there's clear timelines for receiving investigating and resolving complaints and flexibility for the commission
to create rules and procedures to ensure a smooth resolution process the hope is that hearings would be limited to only when absolutely necessary and there should be a lengthy process before you get
get to a hearing giving the standard proof would be the preponderance of the evidence and for those who aren't familiar with that standard that's a standard phrase in the legal parlance if any of you have ever seen the scales of justice what that means is when one side drops below the other by any degree so it doesn't have to be like this it's just preponderance of the evidence is one side weighs more than the other by the slimmest of margins that's what a preponderance of the evidence is that's the standard in most civil proceedings and different than the standard in criminal proceedings which is beyond a reasonable doubt that Commission has subpoena authority that findings be
communicated in writing to both the complainant and the respondent the the
penalties suggested for inclusion are a series of ones which may be issued not
any one particular so these would be in series written reprimand public censure mandatory training training debarment which means not able to contract with the city monetary fines up to a thousand dollars restitution for improper
financial gain disqualification from participation in city contracts referral to state ethics commission or referral to criminal law enforcement if there's been a crime committed with respect to the educational responsibilities which
are required under the Charter in section 12.05 the Commission wishes to have provisions regarding their ability to train both elected appointed and employed officials and to train city residents to increase public awareness of officials responsibilities under the code as appropriate one thing that you won't see in the draft that presented tonight is there other recommendation
and that's because that recommendation would be incorporated into the ordinance that adopts the ethics code and or the admin code and the goal is to combine them both, which is
that they be given up to January 1st, not that it would happen on January 1st, but up until January 21st of 2027 to have the complaint procedures in place, because keep in mind what's going to have to happen here is there's got to be a mechanism for filing complaints. Is that going to be electronic? Is it going to be electronic and paper? What are the ways that's going to happen? That's going to be part of what they're going to have to create. How is that done in a manner of privacy? The hiring of an investigator or investigators to serve the purposes. And maybe equally and more importantly is a time frame to educate all of the city officials,
whether they be employees or elected officials, on the nature of this and their obligation. Because keep in mind, this is going to be something new that is imposed on city employees, which will also mean that the administration will have to have meet and discuss sessions with the relevant unions because it does impact their workplace so there's a whole series of things that would have to happen before they can put all of the provisions in place and so they ask to be given a reasonable amount of time as volunteers to try and do that in one or two months
could be quite a challenge so up to january 1st of 2027 with the hope that you know might get done
significantly sooner than that or sooner than that so with that being said i'll move into the incorporation of these recommendations into
a preliminary draft of the code uh which uh has is now up and what i'll do here is i mean i assume these folks if you want comment you can but uh jade you're the only member of the public so we'll stop occasionally but if you feel like you want to ask a question just do because this This is supposed to be a public workshop with comments and with only five of you in the room I'm more than happy to keep it very flexible and if you folks want to move up closer you're welcome to. I have no problem with that. So the commission did come up with a preamble which was part of the memo to you but for the purpose of the public here I would like to read it. The preamble they would like to see included in the code which I have included is the code
of ethics is meant to establish clear standards to ensure proper use of city resources, protect and safeguard the integrity of public service, and ensure that financial conflicts of interest do not impact the integrity of public service. The purpose of this ethics code and the operation of the ethics commission are to strengthen trust between the people of the city of Lancaster and those chosen to serve them. I must say I applaud them. It's a very well-written preamble. The scope as we indicated which is section two would be all public officials and city
employees and as you scroll down you're going to see city employee means any individual employed by the city of Lancaster in any official capacity and there's a definition for public
officials which basically means all elected officials and appointed officials who have some power and advisory so if you were to create just an advisory body that has no bow no power at all to act under state federal or city ordinance then they wouldn't be subject to this but a body that's acting appointed with some authority given to them by either city ordinance state law or federal law would be subject to this code I will tell you that this code some may ask why is why are we doing this versus just relying on the state ethics code this is in two ways much broader than the state ethics code it's broader in who it applies to so there it's a limited number of individuals at the state ethics code applies to this is broadened out as you can see it's all city employees all public officials that is not the case under the state ethics code it is broader in terms of its definition of nominal or de minimis value which when the state ethics code starts at $500 and with this code the recommendation is $50
and that's what's been incorporated and we'll talk a little bit about how that
plays in it's also broader in its penalties and it's a little bit different in some of its processes so this is in addition to the state ethics Act. We'll see when we get later on that a violation of this act and a penalty issued
under this is not meant to be in lieu of a penalty that you might receive from the state for a violation of the state ethics law, but meant to be in addition. So this is a follow-up
to the Home Rule Study Commission's desire adopted by the electors to have a strong ethics code in place that goes beyond what the current state law does so that takes us into the definitions a couple things here again financial interest includes interest to whether direct or indirect to a city employee the public official
or a member of their immediate family the immediate family definition again is broader than that in the state ethics act it includes parents step parents child, stepchild, sibling, step-sibling, grandparent, grandchild, parent-in-law, sibling-in-law, aunt, uncle, spouse, domestic partner, or first cousin. When you get into financial interest, there is a definition later on for dealing with an ownership interest in an entity. The provisions that I've referenced in this preliminary draft follow the State Ethics Act there, which is a 5% ownership interest or more, would trigger the provisions here.
So that takes us to really from there, once we get past the definitions, we start really getting into what this code does.
And there are six very broad prohibited forms of conduct. of interest, use of public resources inappropriately, use of authority inappropriately, use of confidential
information inappropriately, gifts, as we'll talk about, and post-employment prohibitions. And so those are the six things that this is regulating. One thing to note, and the Commission was very clear in their discussions on this, is this is regulating conduct relating to improper use of your office improper use of city resources this is not conduct regulating conduct that would otherwise be employment conduct behavioral
conduct that is regulated under city policy regulated under labor law regulated under
our union contracts you'll note when we get to the penalty section there's nothing about terminating employees or disciplining employees that is a city function presumptively one of the violations here would be a violation of city policy and would trigger inside the city what disciplinary action might or might not occur through the human resources and disciplinary processes established by the city so the first of these that we'll talk about is conflict of interest. And again, I sort of already tipped the scale and kind of gave away the candy on this one, which is that this is essentially the state act's definition of conflict of interest as it relates to financial gains, with the exception that instead of $500 it's $50 in terms of, you know, receiving something, $50 and under is fine, but over $50 is going
to be a violation or at least required disclosure as we'll talk about. It's also – so it's a conflict to engage in or have financial or other personal interest in any business or transaction defined by the code which is incompatible with the proper discharge of their duties, to engage in or accept private employment or render services
for private interests when that employment of service is incompatible with the proper discharge of their official duties. All of this should seem as common sense, like I think most of us would assume. This is what we would not do anyway because we are of the character that we are and take
the roles and responsibilities we have.
Keep in mind the ethics code is meant to prevent graft, not that we've had any known significant problems with that in the city of Lancaster, but this is again good teaching and to have it legislatively adopted, now everybody will be on the same page and understand what it
is. talk about the exceptions to gifts but essentially you're not supposed to receive or solicit gifts for the work you're doing you can solicit gifts if it's part of your job and by that we're talking about like if you're out soliciting for the city hey we'd like you to help contribute to one of the events the city has that would not obviously be a violation of the ethics code representing private
interest in any action or proceeding against the city um or any of its um authorities agencies boards or commissions right so you you can't come and represent somebody um if you're a city
individual city employee or a public official before a city body because just the the insignia and the title that you have implies that there might be improper influence vote or participate in the negotiation or the making of any contract in which you have a financial interest again this
is fairly logical and apply for and receive publicly funded grant dollars provided by the city and or any subsidiary in an amount to assist with improving their personal or rental property or business right so you shouldn't be taking advantage of city programs as a public official or city employee that are not, that would be coming from the pockets of other city taxpayers.
And Section 5, use of public resources. No public or official or city employee shall use property for their own financial benefit. Well, right, like if I have, I shouldn't be taking city property and using it for gain.
They shouldn't be using it for private use except as specifically prescribed in their employment compensation package.
And the reason that's in there is that, you know, with some of our uniformed officers, there are times where as part of their employment, they're using a city vehicle to come to and from work so that they have that vehicle available in emergency. So we obviously didn't want to put them in position by their employment being already in violation of the Ethics Act.
and no public official or city employee shall use or permit the use of their official title insignia or position in connection with any private business from which they receive compensation or have a financial interest so again don't use the city for your own personal gain you are of service of service means if you're compensated that's the compensation you get but not other
compensation that you might want to take advantage of that's the sort of the give back for being of service um you know i i know that the commission's all heard all this any other comment from public i'll keep i'll keep going then um confidential information um you shouldn't be giving any information not readily available to the public um you shouldn't be using any information that you've gotten that's not readily available to the public again um for a financial interest right so it's it's you're serving of service there is a theme throughout this and it's that financial
draft theme uh section eight details uh in and before i move on any questions from any on counseling feel free to interrupt i know i'm talking so there's a small number here so yeah we can do it informally if anyone needs to stop and ask questions just shout out um section eight deals with you know offering soliciting and accepting gifts that we've already really talked about that there are a list of exceptions in part d and and those are important right so you know a gift occasioned by an immediate family relationship um you could accept that so that gift could be you know we do have employees that might be related right and we might have
employees who are related to public officials um so you know gifts that are related to the family
relationship should not be deemed a violation of the ethics act or the ethics code uh complementary food and refreshment of nominal value remember we had the fifty dollars that uh the commission recommended is what we included here i will note that that fifty dollars is um lower significantly lower than the state ethics act which is 500 other codes have it higher as well it's one of the lower
numbers the lowest i've seen is 25 but i think that was adopted well over 20 years ago so maybe
there's a little bit of a cost-of-living increase when offered by it by sponsoring an organization attended by city officials you know going to ceremonies or events and oftentimes you will get tickets these are available two
tickets per employee per event not to exceed four years there are going to be
events where public officials are invited to attend I'll use an example example, there's the Martin Luther King breakfast every year and a multitude of our public officials
are invited, given tickets. That's not, should be exempt from this. It's, again, that's the type
of thing that we're talking about there. Accompaniment as an immediate family member to a public event or ceremony where the immediate family member is acting in an official capacity.
So again, you know, now your spouse or your significant other, your family member is going to an event and wants to take you and pay for your ticket that should not be a violation memberships events or admissions associated with any boards on which a city employee serves
either in their official capacity or as a private citizen right so you know I used to serve on the board of big brothers little sister big brothers big sisters and you know if I went to an event
and I was given a ticket for that, is that a violation of this? It shouldn't be if I'm actually serving on the board. Non-pecuniary public awards in recognition of public service.
Again, these are exceptions. Gifts from one city employee to another in recognition of a special occasion, illness, or holiday.
You know, we do give gifts to our fellow employees. You know, people retire.
We like to give them a retirement gift. we don't want this to stop us being good people to one another in the workplace non-pecuniary gifts of nominal value reasonable expenses for travel and accommodation where the travel is business related so those are the exceptions the other note here is that again the prohibitions
that were noted are not to be in lieu of the state ethics act but in addition to there's also a section here that says hey look you know public officials might get a gift from a dignitary whether that's a state or federal official or foreign official as long as those gifts are noted and recorded and we'll talk about noting and recording a little bit they should be accepted and they actually become gifts of the city instead of gifts to the individual when a dignitary is doing that that's what that really is and it should be allowed one of the big issues or big changes in this from the state ethics act is section 9 which deals with post-employment restrictions and this is not uncommon in other ethics codes it's not in the state act and it is not anywhere in our current legislation and that's a prohibition from coming back and solicit working on behalf of somebody else to come before the Board of Commission you were working on to get
approval so hey they know me so I'm gonna come back I'm gonna go hire myself out and use my relationships to be able to get them so there's a one-year restriction on that and no one who is for that same 12 months no one who
served as a public official or city employee should personally act in a representative capacity with or without compensation with respect to any case proceeding approval contract or other matter to which that individual as the public official or public employee had substantial participation. So even though there's no compensation, hey, once I'm off, I can't come back and try to move that through for
somebody else. So disclosure and statements of financial interest, the Ethics Commission's recommendations, which I've incorporated here, are that we continue to follow the State
Ethics Act with respect to the filling out and filing of statements of financial interest
by those governed by the State Ethics Act and not pushing that to all city employees
at this point.
Remember, this is broader as to who the code prohibitions apply to, but to be asking all 600 employees and all of our boards and commission members to A, file that form, and then B, who's going to administer that, follow through with it.
there doesn't seem to be a need for that but there's a reservation that they can
ask for it if it's relevant to I'm an investigation and they can get it from the city clerk and that the city clerk should be providing them with a list annually of who they actually who the city clerk actually has received the state of ethics the state ethics act statements of financial disclosure from the next sections relatively significant as well it covers two different things
which is wrongful acts and whistleblower protection and while we talk about
about wrongful acts we're talking about a wrongful complaint so complaints filed when there's no real basis for doing so without any real facts those should be subject to a penalty so that we make sure that what we don't get is a series of complaints that have personal attacks built into them that don't have any merit or basis that are spending city resources in the form of the investigators that are will discuss later and that are involving the
commission time in resolving them. And then a whistleblower protection, which is if you
do report a violation and or you are asked to be interviewed or have to give testimony as part of that, that there shouldn't be any actions or ramifications taken against you for doing so. Again, I think a pretty logical provision, but one if not in, doesn't exist.
The meat and potatoes of what happens if you violate this, which is what most people want
jump to when you start is the violations and penalties section and I referenced them in the in the memo um there's a whole lot of things that should be considered or could be considered
in determining the appropriate penalty including but not limited to severity of the subject's offense position and responsibilities of the subject the presence or absence of any intention on on the part of that individual to conceal deceive or mislead whether the violation was deliberate negligent or inadvertent and whether the incident was isolated or part of a pattern all decisions regarding disciplinary action would in this draft in my preliminary draft to you would require approval by a majority of the commission members not a majority of
a quorum present at a meeting so keep in mind you have a seven member commission so essentially in order to take a disciplinary action or an institute of penalty you need four votes to do so and again this is a little bit of the anti-politicking to make sure that these are significant we're talking about employees we're talking about public officials who may receive a penalty or violation that is gone through the full process and that there is
a majority of the commission that's at least in this draft that's these are all as you're well aware subject to council saying yeah we don't like that it's you're going to be your code but These are the recommendations that I've put in based on the recommendations received from the commission.
Upon any violation of the code provisions, including the undertaking of wrongful acts, there's a series of penalties which may be issued. Not mandatory. These are sort of a menu, and again, it's going to depend on the facts of the particular case
and some of those factors that I just mentioned. They include the admonition, which is basically a letter saying you violated the act. Public censure, which would be a public reprimand regarding that. If you received a financial gain, reimbursement by the city of that financial gain. So there's a financial cost to you. Debarment, again, I mentioned that earlier. And a fine, and I note that it ran together here, so fine should be five. and there should be a separate item, but it's a fine of $1,000, up to $1,000. Referral in cases where the violation of the chapter is also a violation of federal state criminal law, that could be referred to those irrelevant parties. In terms of enforcement of those fines, that would be assigned to the city council solicitor and or the mayor as appropriate and necessary. So to enforce a financial penalty, a public censure would require city council, an admin at admonition would require the director or the mayor so that's where those would come from any questions so a big part of how this would work then is how do we how do we handle complaints houses get processed again what I did just so you're aware of my thought process is I took a look at other ethics Commission I took a look at human relations commissions which are a a similar process where privacy is of utmost importance. And nothing here is shocking or unique. It's sort of a conglomeration of looking at those and thinking about how we do things and the best way to do things to get it accomplished. So again, the composition of the commission is the seven members with the staggered terms. Vacancies get filled as required by the charter,
But in this particular case, they get filled by the individual or entity that appointed the person that made that so that we're not getting into a position where it was council's original appointment, but now the mayor is appointing the replacement. No, the whole purpose that the charter set up was to make sure that there's a series of appointments all from different elected officials, so vacancies would follow that. A requirement that the Ethics Commission select a chairperson and vice chairperson annually,
that a quorum is a majority. It's fairly standard if you've looked at any of our ordinances about creating boards that take action, although the note, again, that for disciplinary action, a majority of the
quorum will not suffice. It's a majority of commission members.
That the meetings are held at the call of the chairperson and that the ethics commission regardless of whether or not they have hearings shall have at least four meetings per year. Again leaving flexibility for them to determine the need for them to meet and how they want to do that. The ethics commission shall appoint an investigating officer.
So this is the investigator that I mentioned earlier. That could be a private investigator. I will say that a lot of ethics commissions use a lawyer because, as we'll go through this, there's a lot of preliminary determinations about probable cause, whether the complaint
has merit to proceed to the next stage.
So oftentimes it's an attorney. If it's an attorney, that attorney could not be in any way related to any of the city
attorneys, couldn't be related to anything, would have to be purely independent. But that's the discretion. They might want to move with a private investigator, an attorney leaving that, but to have an investigating officer.
That gets us to the powers and duties.
We have included in this draft the power to issue advisory opinions.
So if upon request or on their own they want to issue an opinion as to what might or might not constitute a violation of the act, it's allowed to do so. and if it's on the request of an employee and they act in good faith and reliance on that opinion
then they shouldn't be penalized later for doing so right so this is again how do we prevent bad
conduct we ask in advance that's really what that's meant to accomplish like hey if you think
there's a problem go get an opinion from the commission and then you can you can rely on that opinion hold hearings obviously issue subpoenas if they're going to hold hearings they have to
have the ability to issue subpoenas administer oaths and take testimony and issue those orders that we've talked about tonight already when necessary hire independent counsel as we get
through the complaint procedure you're going to see that will be necessary and the mechanism
i've created in this proposed draft for doing so so complaints who can file any person can file a complaint about an alleged violation of the city of lancaster code of ethics if you're going to file a complaint you have to sign it stating that you reasonably believe in
the existence of facts upon which the claim is based and reasonably believe that the complaint is valid under the ethics provisions of the Code of Ethics
and the city's Home Rule Charter I note that I've included that the Ethics Commission may also initiate proceedings on its own so if it becomes aware of something it thinks is a violation it can start this process it would not be
investigating to start keep in mind this would be as we'll get to you're gonna
to see there's a preliminary investigation and a series of investigations.
First look, preliminary, full investigation before it ever gets to the Ethics Commission for a hearing. So how to file, again, I've left this as the Commission needs to determine how complaints will be filed. This would be part of their process early on and to establish rules and regulations
for doing so, the forms for doing so.
So when a complaint is filed, it should be immediately sent to the investigating officer for a preliminary determination.
That preliminary determination is really whether the complaint fall for two things.
Does the complaint fall within the jurisdiction of the ethics commission?
So again, we talked about what are the things that is supposed to be a violation. Our experience with other commissions is that sometimes we get complaints that aren't related to that, and so you don't want to spend a lot of time on those.
We want to make sure it's focused. Again, that's city resources and the purpose that the charter set forth.
And once that preliminary investigation is done by the investigator,
if they determine that it's not valid, that notice is given back and it's done.
Like this is not the subject of the ethics code. If it is, then it moves forward to the next steps of investigation. But there would be an initial review done by the investigator. investigator. That's why, again, you can see why I say oftentimes, and this is a model
that's been followed both in Pittsburgh and Easton, by the way, so I'm not giving you a model that's brand new, but you can see why, at least in one of those jurisdictions, they actually require the investigator to be an attorney, because there is sort of these determinations about what is the meaning of the language in the code itself. That preliminary
investigation has to be completed relatively quickly within 60 days and again if it's if it's finding that there is a reason to move forward then there's a full investigation
the complainant and the commissioner kept advised of this and you know the commission the investigator we can't determine how long an investigation
should take because i simply don't know the facts and some could take a short period of of time some could take a long period of time the goal is to complete it within
absolutely complete it within 180 days that notice should be given to the
complainant at least every 60 days as to the status so it's not always just sitting on no no the investigator needs to keep reporting back and at the conclusion of findings report it's that findings report that triggers what happens next right so if there's a finding of a violation the complainant can then if there's if there's no finding of violation the complaints dismissed if if there is a finding then the complainant the individual who's was complained about has the right to request a hearing within 30 days and
that moves into the hearing process so again it's a whole lot of layers before
we get to a hearing to try and give an opportunity for resolution ultimately once a hearing is held that's where counsel would be assigned the code sets forth that two attorneys should be assigned by the Commission one to represent the Commission and one to represent the essentially the the
investigator and presenting the facts origin I mean they can be appointed by the solicitor but if it's problematic so if my office is at issue i would not appoint them the ethics commission would do that directly again you know for them to have to search out attorneys would be a challenge we're hoping that it wouldn't be my office and that i'd be able to assist in finding counsel who are unbiased and impartial and don't have any conflicts as required but
obviously if i am the subject or it would be problematic for me to be involved even in the the appointment then my me my success or anybody in my office then obviously when we would have a function for them to be able to move past that again upon the
conclusion of the hearing there would need to be a decision and it would have to be in writing there's a process for the individual who's being findings
against a petition for reconsideration again a reiteration that if you complain
you cannot have any adverse employment or other action taken against you a note that all ethics Commission proceedings and records relating to an investigation are confidential until a final determination is made by the
Commission except as may be required to effectuate due process the final order however will become a public record once the subject has exhausted all appeal rights or has failed to timely exercise such rights all other file material remains confidential a provision that says they can adopt rules and regulations to accomplish the functions that are set forth in the in the code and section 14
deals with training which again is preparing and causing prepared and compiled and an ethics manual for distribution to public officials and
city employees providing an overview of the laws regulations which may apply
conducting ethics trainings for public officials and city employees at least one hour per year maybe more if they deem it appropriate and to conduct training as they deem appropriate to the general public because keep in mind this
is supposed to also be made available to those who might want to seek office whether elected or to be appointed to boards and commissions um I strongly suspect that there will be dovetailing of this with some of the training that I give to boards and commission members that i will be giving to elected newly elected officials now that the charter requires that so this is again one of the reasons why i think they need some time to build this to to turn this around in december adopt it and say we're ready to rock and roll on january 1st is probably a bit unrealistic so that's the summary of the draft that i've got
to date and open to questions I have a question for you maybe I missed it somewhere in here is there any provision for appeal whether by the complainant if the violation is not deemed it isn't successful in the preliminary investigation or the investigation process or by the subject so if for the complainant no once the investigator determines that there's no violation or
the board determines there's no violation if it goes all the way that route then there's no appeal to that okay um any act uh that's an official act of the government when it reaches its final
conclusion is appealable to the court of common pleas under state law known as act two so if there is a penalty to be issued or issued there would be another appeal so for example if a council member was was deemed to have violated this and the recommendation is you know whatever well the penalties are that comes after the conclusion of the hearing there is an opportunity because it would be a final act to appeal that to the Court of Common Pleas there would be a large evidentiary record that already exists so you know that's again going to be part and parcel for what happens okay thank you Barry I had a question so it's a little related to that the preliminary investigation if I'm understanding correctly you're saying that if preliminary investing takes place by the private investigator and no
wrongdoing is found it reads as almost like there's no there's no decision to be made by the Ethics Commission it's basically made for them so there's no
it's not if there's none found it's a probable cause standard so there's two parts of the review the first is is their jurisdiction so is this something complained of that is the subject of the ethics code if so then the investigator reports on that and moves to a preliminary investigation preliminary
investigation is simply to determine whether there is probable cause that there may be a violation so in other words if it's reasonable to believe that a violation may have occurred if there's enough evidence to support that this
should move forward to a full investigation then it goes to the full investigation if it's no there's no facts to support this then it ends okay
that makes sense thank you and again that's a preservation of resources um and also um protecting those who are complained about from a process that shouldn't happen if there's nothing that's been presented that it's on its face leaves one to believe it should it should continue
i think where i was kind of like my where my mind was going and um it's just kind of like the idea
that i mean the ethics commission is initiating it right but then if it's you know determined that there's not probable cause um i don't know it's just interesting because it's like the ethics commission started that process but they don't necessarily have a say once that well goes past there's a reason for that so again it's all about objectivity and fairness so they may have heard or
thought there are facts, and so they want to initiate. The point of the initiation is we're asking the investigator to tell us, should this move forward? And if it moves to the point where it comes back to us, that's okay. But ultimately, it's not about we absolutely want to have a violation. If their facts are there, it's going to move forward. But it's really saying that, hey, look, you could hear a whisper down the lane. One of the commission members might have
heard of something, doesn't have the facts, hasn't done a sufficient, hasn't investigated it, so it's an ability to allow, in some ways, without giving a roadmap, somebody to sort
of anonymously make a complaint, right? Like, I can get facts whispered down the lane. Are they worth, is there enough concern that we want to at least have a preliminary review of this by the investigator?
Yes. And the investigator determines what facts are needed to make that determination. But then again, that's where that comes in, making sure that it's objective and you've
hired an objective investigator and that they've been trained and monitored to be consistent in their approach.
MR. That makes sense.
Thank you. MR. Sure. Thank you for the presentation.
And I think my question is a little bit similar to the Consul President's question. Will there be an appeal process if a respondent believes that a fighting was made in error?
MR. Yes.
Again, if you get to a final decision by the Ethics Commission that there's been a violation,
under state law there is a procedure for appealing to the Court of Common Pleas of Lancaster
County for further appeals within the city.
We don't have any more appeals beyond that. Ethics Commission is independent where would that appeal go it can't go to City
Council it can't go to the administration it's just like any other act in the city when there's a final determination here in the city of any kind that can appeal to the Court of Common Pleas of Lancaster County under Act two okay speaking of state law here regarding the financial disclosure it is said that the Commission recommends reliance on existing filings with the city clerk and the State Ethics Commission and how will this city coordinate with this state at the city at the city art the city already does that so that's the city clerk's responsibility currently okay thank you yeah it's no change all that language is saying is that we're not asking for more disclosure statements than the State Ethics Act requires thank you sure any other questions from up here I'll open it up to any questions from the public yes it could be before then but it's a time to establish the procedures right
now if you were to file on January 1st how would they accomplish what's being done the other part of it is to give them time to educate there are 600
employees here of which maybe 25 maybe 50 are currently subject to the State
Ethics Act so you're you're having a significant expansion of who has to comply with this there is a process to go through with union employees to make sure that this flows through with them properly it is not fair to put a burden on them that they're not aware of so to educate them is also relevant and the commission has the obligation to do that it doesn't mean that necessarily a violation didn't occur it's just that we're not going to be able to process complaints until the whole process is
put together oh absolutely and that mr hamburger is that they have up until the end of essentially the end of 2026 but not that they have to wait until that correct and i don't think the goal
is to wait until january 1st but you know these are again seven volunteers and you're going to
to coordinate now interviews of investigators you're going to have to work on creating forms they're not going to be meeting daily like city staff are so there is going to be some
time constraint for them and it would you know they've expressed the they've expressed the desire to have a year to get everything running properly the worst thing to have happen quite frankly is to to put it out and have it have flaws and holes that haven't been thought through
and be ineffective we're we're not we're not adopting this in reaction to any existing problem in the city of lancaster as far as i'm aware there haven't been any significant issues of any kind noted in my 30 years going back to 1994 31 years now geez of of graft or problems with what would
be a violation of the state ethics code and or even this so it's meant to be making sure that government is accountable and trend and transparent and that those who are appointed employed or elected to serve do so with the rights with with with the right thoughts in mind and the right process the process has to start from the back end which what's the process for the complaint and
while there's a lot here um i think there's time and there's still more work to be done to implement it effectively madam president yes if i can interject the um the statements of financial interests that are filed with my office the city is actually uh interpreted that
very broadly um over the years and there are now about 75 annually that are filed
25 more than I guess so there you go we have interpreted broadly so anybody that could
potentially be subject to the state ethics act we've tried to include again as a matter of making
sure that those who are and the state ethics act is really dealing with those who are vested with
the control of funds are reporting the disclosure so that the state ethics board can if necessary determine if there's been any inappropriate transactions great thank you counselors questions from the public Ethics Commission members thank you for your work and your continued work that
they'll be anything else to add mr. Henberger no again I thank counsel for
the opportunity to be of service in these matters I thank these folks behind
me as they've done a really good job of looking at what needs to be included in the code and making what I think are really solid recommendations I will say it's a fairly strong code you know I had I had another attorney take a look at this draft just as I always like to get a second set of eyes on things and and
the comment was well this is significantly stronger than the State Ethics Act and but fair I will say the one place they noted was you know that $50 is that's a number and that was a big debate with with the Commission with ethics commission about what level of of gift and you know i think for uh you know council's perspective you know that that fifty dollars isn't the same as it was yesterday twenty five dollars
isn't either the nice thing here is again this will be adopted by ordinance so if if that if
ultimately the legislative body of the city determines that any part of this needs to be changed it will be able to do so great thank you and on that note what i'll remind uh council is that this isn't a deliberative session so if you've got thoughts further questions clarifying opinions please send them directly to mr hamburger don't copy other members of council on that so that would be a violation of sunshine act if we were to do that i appreciate the information that
you provided in this session and i don't think there's anything else that we need to follow up
on and timeline wise next steps for admin code will be the admin code will
be presented at the committee meeting in December we'll take additional comments thoughts we get back we'll mold them into this one mold this into the admin code so it will be remember we left placeholders in various places there so we'll be cleaning those placeholders up tying all this together and then presenting um the admin code uh as an attachment to an ordinance to adopt it great thank you very
much thank you all right then i think we've concluded our work session this evening counselors Thank you for being here.